大家好，我是Dan Boneh，欢迎来到我的密码学课程
Hello, my name is Dan Boneh, and I'd like to welcome you to my course on cryptography
【ikamusume酱 译注】
这个学季我将在斯坦福大学讲授这门课程
that I'll be teaching at Stanford University this quarter. This quarter, I'm experimenting
我实验一下讲座录像，以便同学在线观看
with recording the lectures and having the students watch the lectures online.
事实上，欢迎任何人观看讲座，加入课程
In fact, anyone is welcome to watch the lectures, and join the course.
此为实验，让我们拭目以待
This is an experiment, so we'll see how it goes. My goals for this
本课程目的是讲授密码学基本原型是如何工作的
course are basically to teach you how cryptographic primitives work.
更重要的，我将告诉大家如何正确使用密码学原型
But more importantly I'd like to teach you how to use cryptographic primitives correctly
以及推导构建加密机制的安全性
and reason about the security of your constructions. We will see various
我们将看到不同的密码学原型的抽象，
还会进行一些安全性证明
abstractions of cryptographic primitives, and we'll do some security proofs.
我的目标是在课程结束后，大家可以推导加密机制的安全性
My goal is that by the end of the course you'll be able to reason about the security of cryptographic
可以破解不安全的加密机制
constructions and be able to break ones that are not secure.
关于如何上本课，简单说两句
Now I'd like to say a few words on how I would like you to take the class. First of all,
首先，我非常推荐听讲座的时候记笔记
I'm a big believer in taking notes as you listen to the lectures. So I would really
我鼓励大家用自己的话归纳总结讲演内容
encourage you to summarize and take notes in your own words of the material that's being presented.
提醒一下，录像的讲演速度比正规课堂快得多
Also I should mention that on the videos, I'm able to go much faster
所以我建议大家
than I would go in a normal classroom. And so I would encourage you to
经常暂停视频，理清讲座内容
periodically pause the video and think about the material that's being covered
知道弄清楚了以后再继续
and not move forward until the material is clear in your mind. Also from time to time,
偶尔视频自动暂停，会有弹出问题
the video will pause and pop-up questions will come up.
它们是帮助大家理解讲座内容的
These are intended to kinda help you along with the material, and I would really encourage you to answer
我建议大家回答这些问题，而不是跳过
those questions by yourselves rather than skip them. Usually the questions
通常这些问题都是关于刚刚讲过的内容，不会太难
are about the material that has just been covered, and so it shouldn't be too difficult to answer
所以我非常鼓励大家去做，而不是跳过
the questions. So I would really encourage you to do them rather than skip them.
现在，我确定上这门课的大家都知道,
密码学在计算机领域无处不在
Now, by now I'm sure everybody taking the class knows that cryptography is used
它是保护数据的常见工具
everywhere computers are. It's a very common tool that's used to protect data.
例如，网页流量可使用HTTPS协议保护
For example, web traffic is protected using a protocol called HTTPS.
无线流量，比如WiFi，可使用WPA2保护
Wireless traffic, for example, Wi-Fi traffic is protected using the, WPA2
WPA2是802.11i的一部分。
手机流量可使用GSM加密机制保护
protocol, that's part of 801.11i. Cell phone traffic is protected
蓝牙流量也可使用密码学保护，等等
using an encryption mechanism in GSM. Bluetooth
traffic is protected using cryptography,
我们将看到这些不同系统是如何工作的
and so on. We're gonna see how these various systems work. In fact, we're gonna
事实上，我们将介绍SSL，还有802.11i的一些细节
cover SSL, and in fact, even 802.11i in quite a bit of detail. And you'll see how
大家会看到这些系统实际应用中是如何工作的。
密码学还可用来保护文件
these system work in practice. Cryptography is also used for protecting files
可以加密存储在硬盘上的文件。如果硬盘被盗
that are stored on disc by encrypting them. So if the disc is stolen,
文件内容也不会被窃取。这也适用于内容保护
the files are not compromised. It's also used for content protection. For example
例如，当你买DVDs和蓝光碟时，上面的电影被加密的
when you buy DVDs and Blu-Ray disks, the movies on these disks are encrypted, in
DVD使用的是CSS系统，也叫内容混淆系统
particular DVD uses a system called CSS, the Content Scrambling System, CSS, and
蓝光碟使用的是AACS系统。
我们会介绍CSS和AACS如何工作
Blu-Ray uses a system called AACS. We'll talk about how CSS and AACS work.
事实上CSS是一个比较容易破解的系统
It turns out that CSS is a fairly easy system to break.
我们将介绍如何分析和破解CSS中的加密
And we'll talk about how, we'll do some cryptanalysis and actually show how to break encryption that's used in CSS.
密码学也可被用于认证
Cryptography is also used for user authentication and in many, many, many
在接下来的几节里用非常多的应用
other applications that we'll talk about in the next segments.  Now I wanna go back
现在我想回到安全通信，讨论这个情况：
我有一台笔记本电脑
to secure communication, and talk about the case where, here, we have a laptop
它正试图与一个网页服务器通信。
这也是介绍我们的朋友们的好机会
trying to communicate with a web server. This is a good time to also introduce our friends,
他们是Alice和Bob，他们贯穿于整个学季
Alice and Bob, who are gonna be with us throughout the quarter. Essentially Alice
Alice总是想与Bob安全通信。
Alice在笔记本一端，Bob在服务器端
is trying to communicate securely with Bob. Here Alice is on the laptop and Bob
使用协议叫做HTTPS，但事实上
is on the server. The protocol that's used to do that is called HTTPS, but in fact,
实际使用的是SSL，有时又叫TLS
the actual protocol is called SSL. Sometimes it's called TLS.
(注意这三个其实是不同的协议)
目的是确保数据在网络中传输时
And the goals of these protocols is to basically make sure that as this data travels across the
首先，攻击者无法窃听数据内容
network, an attacker first of all can't eavesdrop on this data. Second of all, an
其次，攻击者不能修改数据，即无窃听、无篡改
attacker can't modify the data while it's in the network. So no eavesdropping and no tampering.
现在我来谈谈用来保护网页安全的TLS
Now as I said the protocol that's used to secure web traffic called TLS
TLS实际上由两部分组成。第一部分叫做握手协议
actually consists of two parts. The first part is called the handshake protocol
Alice和Bob互相交谈，在握手的最后
where Alice and Bob talk with one another and at the end of the handshake
双方分享一个密钥
handshake basically a shared secret key appears between the two of them. So both
所以Alice和Bob都知道该密钥，
但攻击者不知道会话密钥K
Alice and Bob know this secret key, but an attacker looking at the conversation has
现在，建立密钥，握手
no idea what the key K is. Now, the way you established your secret key, the way
都用到了公钥密码技术
you do the handshake, is using public key cryptography techniques, which we're gonna talk
我们在本课第二部分讨论之。现在Alice和Bob共享密钥
about in the second part of the course. Now once Alice and Bob have the shared key,
你可以使用这个密钥加密数据，安全通信
you can use this key to communicate securely by properly
这是本课的第一部分
encrypting data between them. And in fact this is gonna be the first part of the course,
也就是双方共享密钥时
which is essentially once the two sides have a shared secret key, how do they use
如何使用密钥加密以保护通信数据？
that secret key to encrypt and protect data that goes back and forth between them?
如前所说，密码学另一应用为保护硬盘文件
Now, as I said, another application of cryptography is to protect
这里你有一已加密文件
files on disk. So, here you have a file that happens to be encrypted, so that even
即使硬盘被偷，攻击者其实无法读取文件数据
if the disk is stolen, an attacker can't actually read the contents in the file.
如果攻击者改动硬盘上文件数据
And, if an attacker tries to modify the data on disk, the data in the file while
当Alice试图解密文件时，会检测出改动
it's on disk, when Alice tries to decrypt this file, that will be detected, and
Alice便会忽略文件内容
she'll then basically ignore the contents of the file. So we have both confidentiality
所以我们有文件的私密性和完整性。这里有一点哲学的东西
confidentiality and integrity for files stored on disk. Now I want to make a minor philosophical
事实上加密硬盘上的文件
point, that in fact storing encrypted files on disk is very much the same
与保护Alice和Bob之间的通信很类似
as protecting communication between Alice and Bob. In particular, when you
特别地，当你存储文件在磁盘上时，
基本上是保存文件的Alice明天还想看这个文件
store files on disk, it's basically Alice who stores the file today wants to read
所以与Alice和Bob通信不同
the file tomorrow. So rather than communicating between two parties Alice and Bob,
存储文件加密就是今天的Alice
in the case of a stored disk encryption, it's Alice today who is
和明天的Alice通信
但这两种情形：安全通信和安全文件
communicating with Alice tomorrow. But really the two scenarios, secure
从哲学上讲是一样的
communications, and secure files, are kind of philosophically the same. Now, the
以分组的形式保护流量的技术叫做对称加密
building block for securing traffic is what's called symmetric encryption
在本课的第一部分，我们将详细介绍
systems. And we're gonna talk, in the first half of the course extensively about
对称加密系统。在对称加密系统中
symmetric encryption systems. So in a symmetric encryption system, basically, the two parties,
Alice和Bob双方共享密钥k
攻击者不知道密钥k
Alice and Bob, share a secret key k, which the attacker does not
只有通信双方知道密钥k
现在他们将使用两个算法进行秘密通信
know. Only they know the secret key k. Now, they're gonna use a cipher which
两个算法分别是E和D。
E是加密算法，D是解密算法
consists of these two algorithms, E and D. E is called an encryption algorithm and D
加密算法以原信息和密钥为输入
is called the decryption algorithm. The encryption algorithm takes the message and
产生相应密文
the key as inputs, and produces a corresponding ciphertext. And the
解密算法则正好相反
它以密文和密钥为输入，输出原信息
decryption algorithm does the opposite. It takes the ciphertext as input along with the key
现在有一点很重要
key and produces the corresponding message. Now, a very important point that
我需要强调，我只说一次
I would like to stress. I'm only gonna say this once now and never again, but it is an
尽管它很重要：
算法E和D，即实际加密算法
extremely important point. And that is: that the algorithms E and D, the actual
它们是面向公众公开的
攻击者知道算法是如何工作的
encryption algorithms are publicly known. Adversary knows exactly how they work. The
只有密钥k是保密的
only thing that's kept secret is the secret key k. Other than that
其余都是公开的
明白这一点很重要
everything else is completely public and it's really important to realize that you
你应当只使用公开的加密算法
should only use algorithms that are public because those algorithms have been
因为公开算法已被数以百计的业内人士
检查了很多很多年
peer-reviewed by a very large community of hundreds of people for many, many, many years,
而且只有业内证实无法破解这些算法
它们才开始被使用
and these algorithms only begin to be used once this community has shown that
事实上，如果有人跟你说
嘿，我有一个私有的加密方法
they cannot be broken, essentially. So in fact, if somebody comes to you and says, hey, I have a proprietary
问你要不要用。答案通常是
cipher that you might want to use, the answer usually should be that
坚持标准算法，摒弃私有算法
you stick to standards, to standard algorithms, and not use a proprietary
事实上，有很多私有加密算法的例子
cipher. In fact, there are many examples of proprietary ciphers that, as soon as
它们一旦被逆向工程，很容易被分析破解
they were reverse engineered, they were easily broken by simple analysis.
我们将在课程的第一部分讨论
即使在对称加密的一些简单情形中
Now, even in the simple cases of symmetric encryption which we're gonna discuss
我们将讨论两种情况
in the first half of the course, there are actually two cases that we're gonna discuss in turn.
第一，每个密钥只加密一个信息
The first, is when every key is only used to encrypt a
我们叫一次密钥。举个例子
single message, we call these one time keys. Okay. So for example, when you
当你加密电子邮件时，
通常不同邮件使用不同密钥加密
encrypt email messages, it's very common that every single email is encrypted using
对吧？不同的对称密钥
a different symmetric key. Yeah? Different symmetric cipher key. Because the key is
因为一个密钥只加密一个信息
有很多有效简便的方法
used to encrypt only one message there are actually fairly efficient and simple ways of
可以用一次密钥进行加密
我们在下一模块进行讨论
encrypting messages using these one time keys and we'll discuss those actually
还有许多情况是用密钥加密多个信息
in the next module. Now there are many cases in fact where keys
我们称之为多次密钥
need to be used to encrypt multiple messages. We call these many time keys.
例如，加密文件系统里的文件
同一密钥用来加密很多不同的文件
For example, when you encrypt files in a file system the same key is used
事实上，如果用一个密钥加密多个信息
to encrypt many many, different files. And it turns out if the key is now going to be used to encrypt
我们需要更多的机制来确保加密系统是安全的
multiple messages, we need a little bit of more machinery to make sure that the
事实上，在我们讨论一次性密钥之后
encryption system is secure. In fact after we talk about the one-time keys, we
我们还将谈谈为多次密钥设计的加密机制
will move over and talk about encryption modes that are specifically designed for
我们将会看到为了确保安全
many-time keys. And we'll see that there are a couple more steps that need to be taken to
需要有更多的步骤。好，最后我说一点
ensure security in those cases. Okay, the last point I wanna make
关于密码学有几点特别重要，需要记住
is that there are a couple of important things to remember about cryptography. First of all,
首先，密码学当然是保护计算机信息的优秀工具
cryptography, of course, is a fantastic tool for protecting information in computer systems.
但是，很重要的是，密码学也有其局限性
However, it's also very important that cryptography has its limitations.
首先，密码学不能解决所有安全问题
First of all, cryptography is really not the solution to all security problems.
例如，如果软件有bug，
通常密码学无能为力
For example, if you have software bugs then very often cryptography is not
类似的，如果你担心社会工程的攻击
going to be able to help you. Similarly, if you're worried about social engineering attacks,
比如攻击者试图欺骗用户去做
会伤害到用户自己的事
where the attacker tries to fool the user into taking actions
那么这时密码学通常派不上用场
that are going to hurt the user, then cryptography is very often actually not
这点很重要，尽管密码学很厉害
going to help you. So it's very important that although it's a fabulous tool, it's not the
但它不是解决安全问题的万能钥匙
另一非常重要的一点是
solution to all security problems. Now another very important point is that cryptography
如果实现不正确，密码学将是无用的
essentially becomes useless if it's implemented incorrectly. So, for example,
例如，有很多系统正常工作
there are a number of systems that work perfectly fine. And we'll see examples of those
我们会看到这样的系统，允许Alice和Bob通信
systems, that, in fact, allow Alice and Bob to communicate. And,
信息由Alice发向Bob，
Bob接收并解密
in fact, messages that Alice sent to Bob, Bob can receive and decrypt. However,
但是由于密码学不正确地实现，
系统完全是不安全的
because cryptography is implemented incorrectly, the systems are completely insecure.
这里我应该提及一个老的加密标准WEP
Actually I should say that I like to mention an old encryption standard
WEP用来加密WiFi流量的
called WEP this is used for encrypting Wi-Fi traffic. WEP contains many
WEP有很多错误，本课里我会为大家展示
mistakes in it and often when I wanna show you how not to do things in cryptography
我会以WEP的内容为例，对我来说
有这样一个协议为例很是幸运
I will point to how things were done in WEP as an example. So for me, it's very fortunate to have an example,
我能告诉大家如何避免这些错误
a protocol I can point to for how not to do things. And finally, a very
另一个非常重要的是
important point that I'd like you to remember is that cryptography is not
密码学不是让你自己去发明设计
something you should try to invent and design yourself. As I said, there are
我说过，密码学有标准，我们会详细讨论
standards in cryptography, standard cryptographic primitives which we're gonna discuss
这些标准化的密码学原型
at length during this course. And primarily you're supposed to use
你只需使用这些标准，而不是发明它们
these standard cryptographic primitives, and not invent things, these primitives,
这些标准经历了多年数百人的检验
yourself. The standards have all gone through, many years of
它们不是随意设计的
review by hundreds of people, and that's not something that's going to happen to an ad hoc design.
我说过，多年来有很多随意设计的加密机制
And, as I said, over the years there are many examples of
一经分析即被攻破
ad hoc designs that were immediately broken as soon as they were analyzed.